Guide to the Joseph A. Sinsheimer Papers, 1962-1987 RL.10056
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Interviews and speeches, 1963-1987; 1; 6 Linear Feet 157 items, 8 single-row cassette boxes, 2 paige boxes
  - Machesky, Nathaniel interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 June 26; 27
    Catholic priest in Greenwood during most of the 1960s; founder of the St. Francis Center in the heart of black Greenwood; active supporter of the civil rights movement. Interview with Sinsheimer. Machesky discussed: Dick Gregory's effort to bring food to black Greenwood in the winter of 1962-1963; the formation of a weekly newsletter, The Center Light, to serve black Greenwood; the relationship between Greenwood's white Catholics and black community; development of economic boycotts in Greenwood, 1967-1969; the formation of a credit union in Greenwood to serve the town's black population; the role of various white leaders in Greenwood, 1962-1963.
    - Transcript (Box 1)
  - McGhee, Silas interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1987 February 25; 28
    Civil rights activist in Greenwood, MS. Interview with Sinsheimer. McGhee discussed: his reaction to the Freedom Rides and the North Carolina sit-ins in 1960-1961; his attempt to integrate the Leflore Theater in Greenwood in 1963; speaking at a mass meeting in Clarksdale, MS; working to organize the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party in the state; the organization of a SNCC "folk festival" on his family's property in 1963 that featured a performance by Bob Dylan; reaction to Medgar Evers' shooting in Greenwood.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0077)
    - Transcript (Box 1)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0026)
  - McLemore, Dr. Leslie interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 February 14; 29
    Vice-chair of the Mississippi Freedom Democratic Party, 1964. Interview with Sinsheimer. McLemore discussed: his work for the MFDP during the summer of 1964; leadership qualities of Robert Moses; Moses' relationship with Amzie Moore; leadership qualities of Fannie Lou Hamer; Martin Luther King's role at the 1964 Democratic National Convention; Aaron Henry's role at the 1964 Democratic National Convention.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0078)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0027)
  - Moore, James interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 June 18; 31
    Prominent civil rights activist in Greenwood, MS. Interview with Sinsheimer. Moore discussed the development of the Greenwood campaign, 1962-1963.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0080)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0029)
  - Moses, Robert - speech, 1980 February 3; 32
    Transcript of Moses' comments at the Conference on Ethics and Morality: Voices of the Civil Rights Movement in Washington, D.C.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0081)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0030)
  - Moses, Robert interviewed by John Dittmer, 1983 August 15; 34
    Interview with John Dittmer. Moses discussed: his voter registration work in Southwest Mississippi in 1961; the statewide organization of white resistance to civil rights work; his feelings following the MFDP challenge at the 1964 Democratic National Convention; Amzie Moore's role in the Mississippi movement; the NAACP in Mississippi; the role of white students in the 1964 Freedom Summer Project; tensions between different civil rights groups working in Mississippi; a proposed literacy project in Mississippi in 1964-1965.
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Moses, Robert interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1983 November 19; 33
    Interview with Sinsheimer.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0082)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0031)
  - Moses, Robert interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1984 April 11; 35
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0084)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0033)
  - Moses, Robert interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1984 December 5; 36
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0085)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0034)
  - Moses, Robert - speech, 1987 June 8; 37
    Transcript of a speech delivered at the Organizers Training Center 15th Anniversary Dinner, San Francisco, CA. Discussed the role of Ella Baker, Hazel Palmer, and Fannie Lou Hamer. Also references the Duke Leadership Program from 1985.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0086)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0035)
  - Palmer, Hazel interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 June 19
    Local activist from Jackson, MS, who became active in Mississippi in the early 1960s; went on to become a MFDP delegate to the 1964 Democratic National Convention. Interview with Sinsheimer.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0088)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Palmer, Hazel interviewed by Robert Moses, session 1, 1985 October 26; 38
    Interview with Robert Moses as part of a Duke Leadership Program.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0087)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0036)
  - Palmer, Hazel interviewed by Robert Moses, session 2, 1985 October 26
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0037)
  - Palmer, Hazel interviewed by Robert Moses, session 3, 1985 October 26
    - Original audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0089)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 of 2 (unidentified interviewee on side 2) (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0079)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0038)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0028)
  - Payne, Bruce interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1983 March 18; 39
    Student at Yale University and one of the first northern white students to volunteer in Mississippi. Interview with Sinsheimer. Payne discussed: Allard Lowenstein's role in recruiting students to the Mississippi movement; Robert Moses' leadership style; the importance of the 1963 Freedom Vote in the Mississippi campaign.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0090)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0039)
  - Payne, Bruce interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1983 October 24; 40
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0091)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0040)
  - Peacock, Willie interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 February 8; 41
    SNCC field secretary in Mississippi, 1962-1965; particularly active in Greenwood during the 1963 voter registration campaign. Interview with Sinsheimer. Peacock discussed: the development of the NAACP chapter at Rust College in 1961 following the Greensboro sit-ins; meeting Robert Moses in Fall 1961; renewal of the Marshall County Voter's League, 1962; Amzie Moore's relationship with Robert Moses and other young SNCC organizers; formation of a SNCC singing quartet with Peacock and Hollis Watkins; working on voter registration activity in Sunflower County with Fannie Lou Hamer; assassination attempt on Jimmy Travis and Robert Moses outside Greenwood in 1963; problems in the 1964 Freedom Summer Project.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0092)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0041)
  - Pilcher, Mattie interviewed by Howard Zinn, 1963 August 15; 42
    Active in the 1963 civil rights demonstrations in Greenwood. Interview with Howard Zinn. Pilcher discussed: her personal family history in Greenwood; changes in Greenwood's race relations as a result of civil rights activity; the arrival of SNCC coordinator Samuel Block in Greenwood; attendance at a SNCC mass meeting featuring comedian Dick Gregory; attendance at SNCC-sponsored voter registration classes; her son's decision to attend Tougaloo College.
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Rustin, Bayard - speech, 1963 December 1; 43
    Transcript of a speech delivered at the Fourth Annual SNCC Conference, Washington, D.C.
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Sellers, Cleveland interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 March 30; 44
    Former SNCC field secretary. Interview with Sinsheimer. Sellers discussed: his tenure at Howard University as a student and a civil rights activist; class divisions among the student population at Howard; his first encounters with Malcolm X during the summer of 1963; the impact of Emmett Till's murder on his political development; tensions between SNCC staff and the summer volunteers at Ohio training sessions for the 1964 Freedom Summer Project; Robert Moses' leadership role at the Ohio training sessions; searching for the bodies of the three "missing" civil rights workers in Philadelphia, MS; working in Holly Springs, MS, during the 1964 Freedom Summer Project; John Doar's efforts to protect civil rights workers in Mississippi; sexual tensions between black SNCC staffers and white volunteers; his role in coordinating MFDP activities at the Democratic National Convention; internal discussions among MFDP leaders in response to the Johnson administration's proposed "compromise."
    - Original audiocassette, 1 of 3 (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0093)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 of 3 (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0094)
    - Original audiocassette, 3 of 3 (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0095)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 1 of 3 (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0042)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 2 of 3 (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0043)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 3 of 3 (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0044)
  - Sitton, Claude interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 January 21; 45
    Former reporter for the New York Times based in Atlanta; covered many major civil rights stories in Mississippi during the early 1960s. Interview with Sinsheimer. Sitton discussed: the disappearance of three civil rights workers during the 1964 Freedom Summer Project; violence associated with SNCC's voter registration activities in McComb, MS; response of the U.S. Justice Dept. to major events in Mississippi.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0096)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0045)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Smith, Frank interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1986 May 23; 47
    Former SNCC field secretary from Mississippi. Interview with Sinsheimer. Smith discussed: his civil rights activities in Holly Springs, MS; Moses' leadership role in Mississippi; the role of white students in the Mississippi civil rights movement; SNCC's efforts in Greenwood, MS; his reaction to the assassination of Medgar Evers; his experience in organizing voter registration drives in Hattiesburg, MS; James Forman's influences on SNCC staff in Mississippi; Aaron Henry's role in the Mississippi campaign.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0098)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0047)
  - Smith, Rev. R.L.T. interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 February 12; 48
    Prominent civil rights leader from Jackson, MS; ran for U.S. House of Representatives in 1962 in a campaign managed by Robert Moses. Interview with Sinsheimer. Smith discussed: his relationship with Amzie Moore; Robert Moses' influence on the movement; his decision to run for Congress in 1962; campaigning in rural Mississippi; the role of moderate newspapers in the state.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0099)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0048)
  - "Story of Greenwood, Mississippi" - recording, 1963; 49
    Transcript of recording produced for SNCC by Guy Carawan, Folkway Records, NY. Includes Robert Moses, Dave Sanders, Fannie Lou Hamer, Cleveland Jordan, Willie Peacock, Alice Blackman, Hollis Watkins, Dick Gregory, Medgar Evers, and Rev. Barber.
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Taylor, Lola and Laura interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 June 18; 50
    - Original audiocassette (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0080)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0029)
  - Thomas, Norman - press conference, 1963 November; 51
    Transcript of the SNCC Press Conference at the Fourth Annual SNCC Conference, Washington, D.C. Features Julian Bond, Norman Thomas, Robert Moses, James Forman, Bill Hanson, and Frank Smith.
    Rights to this item have not been shared with the donor or the Rubenstein Library. Please contact the Rubenstein Library for further information on accessing this resource.
    - Transcript (Box 2)
  - Thrasher, Sue interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1983 November 11; 52
    One of the first white students to get involved with the Southern civil rights movement; founder of the Southern Student Organizing Committee (SSOC); student volunteer in Biloxi during the 1964 Freedom Summer Project. Interview with Sinsheimer.
    - Original audiocassette (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0100)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0049)
  - Watkins, Hollis interviewed by Joseph Sinsheimer, 1985 February 13-14; 53
    SNCC field secretary. Two interviews with Sinsheimer.
    - Original audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0101)
    - Original audiocassette, 2 of 2 (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0102)
    - Transcript (Box 2)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 1 of 2 (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0050)
    - Use copy audiocassette, 2 of 2 (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0051)
  - Unknown, undated
    - Original audiocassette, mislabeled "Robert Moses, November 19, 1983" (Box 7, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0083)
    - Use copy audiocassette, mislabeled "Robert Moses, November 19, 1983" (Box 4, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0032)
    - Original audiocassette, mislabeled "Frank Smith, June 28, 1985" (Box 8, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0097)
    - Use copy audiocassette, mislabeled "Frank Smith, June 28, 1985" (Box 5, Audio-cassette RL10056-CS-0046)
- Accompanying Materials, 1962-1993; 2 boxes
  Original correspondence, research files, scrapbooks, and supplemental information collected by Sinsheimer in support of his oral history project.
  - Scrapbooks, 1962-1964, 2 Volumes (Box 9)
    Two scrapbooks with photocopied/photostat newspaper clippings covering the civil rights movement. Clippings include some articles written by Robert Moses. Articles cover voting rights, poll taxes, violence against and jailing of African Americans, and Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) activities, many of them in Mississippi.
  - Robert Moses interview transcript and materials, 1964-1982 (Box 10)
    Includes a Smithsonian article on Moses, transcripts of his remarks at the National Museum of American History and a 1982 interview, and a reprint of a 1964 speech.
  - Robert Moses transcripts, 1963, 1978, and undated (Box 10)
    Amzie Moore's funeral, Nov. 1963; 4th Annual SNCC Conference, Feb. 1963; Atlanta SNCC Conference, 1978; Ella Jo Baker's birthday; and interview with John Dittmer.
  - John Dittmer papers, 1964-1985 (Box 10)
    "The Movement in McComb (1961-1964)" and "In the Name of Freedom: The Politics of the Mississippi Movement, 1954-1964."
  - Court Records and letters to Senator Hubert Humphrey and John F. Kennedy, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1963-1985 (Box 10)
    Clippings regarding civil rights in the South from Human Organization, The Reporter, and others. Also includes "Revolution in Mississippi," a publication from Students for a Democratic Society.
  - Manuscript for book on Robert Moses by Eric R. Burner, 1993, 2 folders (Box 10)
    Letter and manuscript for book to be published by New York University Press.
  - Speeches, letters, interviews, and surveys, 1963-1977 (Box 10)
    Lengthy correspondence from Henry Aronson and Stephen Bingham; speech entitled "The Sense and the Use of History by Mississippians in the Movement Struggles;" 1977 Interview with Allard Lowenstein; 1963 Report from SNCC Field Secretary; and "Reflections on Martin Luther King Jr.--And Us," among other materials.
  - "Freedom Summer" Tougaloo College conference proceedings, 1979 (Box 10)
  - Photographs: MFDP State Convention and Voter Registration, 1963-64 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 1981-1983 (Box 10)
    Signs and Cities by Elizabeth Sewell, Mississippi Folklore Register, and Southern Exposure: Stayed on Freedom, 1981